Harry L. Custard Papers
Harry L. Custard Papers
1902-1967
Custard, Harry Lewis, 1893-1966.
9 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, philosopher, educator. Papers pertain to Custard's work in the philosophical field of the Unity of Knowledge. Correspondents whose letters are of significant depth and/or duration include William Moseley Brown, Luther L. Castetter, George R. Clements, Newton Dillaway, Laurence Foster, Isabel B. Holbrook, Robert Maynard Hutchins, C.G. Jung, Raymond Frank Piper, J. Hugo Tatsch, William Pearson Tolley, Margaret Truman, and Howard John Zitko.
148921
Biographical History
Harry Lewis Custard (1893-1966) was an American author, philosopher, and educator. Born in Stroudsburg, Pennsylvania, Custard lived in Scranton until he attended Syracuse University from 1916-1918, at which time military service interrupted his studies. He was able, however, to finish school while in the service and graduated in 1920. He went on to attend Harvard Graduate School of Business Administration from 1920-1922. He later taught at Lehigh University and Simmons College after which he worked for the federal government. With his wife, Edith May, he authored The Unity of Knowledge and the Organization of Thought (1940).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Harry L. Custard Papers consists of general files, memorabilia, published material, and writings. The entire collection pertains to Custard's work in the philosophical field of "unity of knowledge."
General files contains files of information on various subjects which interested Custard as well as files of correspondence with people who expressed an interest in his research. This series also contains games devised by Custard, complete with playing cards and rules. Biographical material may be found in the "Personal" folder. Of particular interest to the researcher may be the signed letter from Margaret Truman in the "Graphology: signatures" folder and a signed letter from C. G. Jung in the first folder of "Correspondence: General: 1934-1948."
Memorabilia contains two items, a Harvard business school yearbook (1926-1927) and a Tambourine and Bones Award.
Published material contains articles written by Custard's wife Edith as well aas books on subjects related to Custard's research.
Writings contains typescripts and published examples of Custard's work, along with notes of various types (daily jottings, notes on books he read, and similar).
Arrangement of the Collection
General files are in alphabetical order by subject. Published material and writings are in alphabetical order by type and within that by title.
Related Material
has made a concerted effort over the years to ensure that its manuscript and rare books holdings complement each other. As a result, many of our manuscript collections are supported by books, pamphlets, serials and other items which are cataloged in the Rare Books Collection. Please be sure to search for these related materials.
See also the
Jeremiah Custard Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Religion and philosophy; Brown, William Moseley, 1894-; Castetter, Luther L., 1895-; Clements, George R.; Custard, Edith May (Best), 1900-; Custard, Harry Lewis, 1893-1966 Archives.; Dillaway, Newton, 1904-; Foster, Laurence, 1903-1969.; Holbrook, Isabel B.; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977.; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961.; Piper, Raymond Frank.; Tatsch, J. Hugo (Jacob Hugo), 1888-1939.; Tolley, William Pearson, 1900-; Truman, Margaret, 1924-; Zitko, Howard John, 1911-; Authors, American.; Educators -- United States.; Knowledge, Theory of.; Philosophers -- United States.; Philosophy, Modern.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Notes (documents); Authors.; Educators.; Philosophers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- General files
  - Advertising for Unity of Knowledge publications, 1949-1956 (Box 1)
  - American Engineering Council, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Character study (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1930-1951 (Box 1)
  - Color and music, 1922-1933 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Advertising, 1949-1960 (Box 1)
    - Roger Babson, 1932-1934 (Box 1)
    - Edith M. Barrett, 1933-1948 (Box 1)
    - Charles Bollinger, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
    - Roger Borsodi, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - William Mosely Brown and J. Hugo Tatsch, 1933-1965 (Box 1)
    - Keral Carsen, 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - L.L. Castetter, 1952-1966 (Box 1)
    - Dr. George R. Clements, 1957-1966 (Box 1)
    - Gerald J. Defraeye, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Newton Dillaway, 1953-1966; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The Essenes, 1944-1948 (Box 1)
    - General
      - 1932-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1932-1967 (Box 1)
      - 1933-1957 (Box 1)
      - 1934-1948, includes signed letter from C.G. Jung; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1942-1951, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1942-1962 (Box 1)
      - 1949-1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Ellen Gibbs, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - J.B. Goldstone, 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - Health Research, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Charles W. Hendel, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth Hadley Hunt, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Hobart Huson, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
    - Dr. Robert M. Hutchins, 1933-1967 (Box 1)
    - George Winthrop Lee, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - Letters of recommendation and photostats, 1919-1948 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Raymond F. Piper, 1924-1950 (Box 1)
    - John A. Polak, 1948-1965 (Box 1)
    - S. Radhakrishnan, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Theodor A. Reich, 1936-1949 (Box 1)
    - Oliver L. Reiser, 1947-1965 (Box 1)
    - R.C. Roper, 1940-1953 (Box 2)
    - Thomas Sugrue, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Mark Sullivan (Box 2)
    - B.G.H. Vanderjagt, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Charles Weller, 1946-1948 (Box 2)
    - Dr. Howard Zitko, 1962-1967; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and interviews, 1933-1950 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1952-1956 (Box 2)
  - Distribution of Journal of Social Psychology, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Educational Research Associates (Box 2)
  - Employment in government service, 1937-1961 (Box 2)
  - Dr. Laurence Foster, 1949-1965 (Box 2)
  - Louis Freiberg, 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - Games
    - Business Lingo (Box 2)
    - The Business Race Track (Box 2)
    - Double Checkers (Box 2)
    - The Family Circle Target Game (Box 2)
    - Family Lingo (Box 2)
    - Science Lingo (Box 2)
  - Graphology
    - Handwriting samples and signatures (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Published material (Box 2)
    - Signatures, includes signed letter from Margaret Truman (Box 2)
  - Isabel B. Holbrook, 1915-1935 (Box 2)
  - Isabel B. Holbrook (oversize) (Oversize 1)
  - Library of Congress, 1945-1965 (Box 2)
  - Library of Congress cards for Custard's books (Box 2)
  - List of religious systems and sects (Box 2)
  - Gilbert Lorenz, 1958-1965 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous published material, 1930-1966 (Box 2)
  - Organic gardening (Box 2)
  - Original sheet music, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Personal, 1902-1966; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Quotations, 1920-1946 (Box 2)
  - Oliver L. Reiser (Box 3)
  - Sevens (Box 3)
  - Gordon Speedie (Box 3)
  - Statements pertaining to the Unity of Knowledge (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University Class Reunion, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Giorgio Tagliacozzo, 1964 (Box 3)
  - William P. Tolley, 1963-1965 (Box 3)
  - Unit of Knowledge publications (Box 3)
  - Watches (Box 3)
  - Julius M. Werner, 1966 (Box 3)
  - World University development program, 1960-1966; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Harvard Business School yearbook, 1926-1927 (Box 3)
  - Tambourine and Bones award (Box 3)
- Published material
  - Articles
    - "On Relations" (Box 3)
  - Books
    - Miscellaneous, 13 volumes (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 22 volumes (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 11 volumes (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 13 volumes (Box 6)
  - Magazines
    - The Antioch Review, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Fortune, Nov 1943 (Oversize 1)
    - Higher Education for American Democracy, volumes I-VI, 1947; 10 volumes (Box 7)
    - Life, 28 Sep 1942 (Oversize 1)
    - Main Currents in Modern Thought, 1946-1948; 6 issues (Box 7)
    - Mind Digest, 1946; 3 issues (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets
    - A Philosophy for World Unification, 1946; 4 copies (Box 7)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Published
      - "Emerson on health, 1956 (Box 7)
      - "Unity of Knowledge", 1964-1965; 2 issues (Box 7)
    - Typescripts
      - "The Beard Five-Year Plan in Reflection", 1931 (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous, 1933-1953; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - "The Unity of Knowledge; Unity of the Human Soul" (Box 7)
      - "The Unity of Matter" (Box 7)
  - Books
    - Published
      - The Unity of Knowledge and the Organization of Thought
        - Excerpts, 1934; 2 copies (Oversize 1)
        - Published, 1940; 3 volumes (Oversize 1)
    - Typescripts
      - The Essence of Emerson, 1955 (Box 7)
      - The Geometry of Thought, 1959 (Box 7)
      - The Nature of Economics in the Economy of Nature, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Orientation in Education, 1934 (Box 7)
      - Orientation in the Sphere of Knowledge, 1958 (Box 7)
      - Orientation in the Sphere of Philosophy, 1958 (Box 7)
      - Orientation in the Spheres of Economics and Business, 1959 (Box 7)
      - Philosopher Joe, 1958 (Box 7)
      - The Rhythmic Road of Life, 1958 (Box 7)
      - Seeing Life Whole, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Seeing Things Whole, 1949 (Box 7)
      - The Unity in Religion, 1955 (Box 7)
      - The Universal Reference Frame, 1958 (Box 7)
      - The Universe and the University, 1965 (Box 7)
      - Wisdom of Emerson, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Daily notes and jottings
    - 1929-1965 (Box 8)
    - 1930-1944 (Box 8)
    - 1930-1966 (Box 8)
    - 1945-1960 (Box 8)
  - Early charts, notes and quotations
    - Miscellaneous, 1930 (Box 8)
  - Essays
    - "What Woodrow Wilson means to me" (Box 8)
  - Notes
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1933-1965 (Box 8)
      - 1941-1964 (Box 8)
    - Orientation in Education (Box 8)
    - Reading notes, 9 folders (Box 8)
  - Published material, 34 volumes
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - The Sphere of Graphology (Box 9)